Guide to the Samuel Solomon papers, 1932-1964 MS2092
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Hearings, 1940-1946; MS2092 Series 2; 1 Linear feet (Box 24, Box 25)
  This series consists of transcripts of hearings before the Civil Aeronautics Board. The Civil Aeronautics Board promoted and regulated the civil air industry within the United States and between the United States and foreign countries in the interest of the foreign and domestic commerce of the United States, the postal service, and the national defense. In 1940, President Franklin Roosevelt split the authority into two agencies, the Civil Aeronautics Administration (CAA) and the Civil Aeronautics Board (CAB). The CAA was responsible for air traffic control, safety programs, and airway development. The CAB was entrusted with safety rulemaking, accident investigation, and economic regulation of the airlines. Although both organizations were part of the Department of Commerce, the CAB functioned independently.
  The Federal Aviation Agency Act of 1958 transferred safety rulemaking from Civil Aeronautics Board to the new FAA, and also gave the FAA sole responsibility for a common civil-military system of air navigation and air traffic control. In 1967, a new National Transportation Safety Board took over the CAB's role of investigating aviation accidents.
  The Civil Aeronautics Board was abolished January 1, 1985.
  - Before the Civil Aeronautics Board Exhibits of Atlantic Airlines, Inc. re: Docket No. 674 et al. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Before the Civil Aeronautics Board Exhibits of Atlantic Airlines, Inc. re: Docket No. 730 et al. [1/2] (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Before the Civil Aeronautics Board Exhibits of Atlantic Airlines, Inc. re: Docket No. 730 et al. [2/2] (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Before the Civil Aeronautics Board Exhibits of Atlantic Airlines, Inc. re: Docket No. 730 et al. [1/2] (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Before the Civil Aeronautics Board Exhibits of Atlantic Airlines, Inc. re: Docket No. 730 et al. [2/2] (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Boston-Maine Airways, Inc. Docket No. 219 Oral Argument Vol. 1 pgs 1-27, 06/05/1940 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Boston-New York-Atlanta-New Orleans Case Docket 730 et al Vol. 18 pages 3583-3745, 07/12/1946 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Boston-New York-Atlanta-New Orleans Case Docket No. 730 et al Vol. 16 pgs 3280-3430, 06/29/1946 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Boston-New York-Atlanta-New Orleans Case Docket No. 730 et al Vol. 19 pgs 3923-4020, 07/08/1946 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Exhibits of California Eastern Airways, Inc. Docket No. 3397, et al (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Middle Atlantic Area Case Docket No. 674 et al pgs. 2537-2593, 02/19/1946 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Middle Atlantic Area Case Docket No. 674 et al pgs. 3538-3586, 02/27/1946 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Middle Atlantic Area Case Docket No. 674 et al Vol. 23 pgs. 3587-3748, 02/28/1946 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Middle Atlantic Area Case Docket No. 674 et al Vol. 24 pgs. 3749-3861, 03/01/1946 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Middle Atlantic Area Case Docket No. 674 et al Vol. 26 pgs. 4096-4213, 03/05/1946 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board Middle Atlantic Area Case Docket No. 674 et al pgs. 2910-2914; 3865-3868; 3872-3886 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Atlantic Airlines, Inc. CAB Docket No. 674 et al (Box 29, Folder 1)
- Printed materials, 1940-1966; MS2092 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 27, Box 26)
  This series consists of pamphlets, magazines, and reports related to aviation.
  - Air Board Technical Notes issued by Controller Technical Department (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Computer Simulation of Airport Operations Applied to Development Planning New Jersey-New York Metropolitan Area, 09/1966 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - A Chronicle of the Aviation Industry in America 1951 supplement (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - A Chronicle of the Aviation Industry in America 1903-1947 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Flight log of TWA Constellation Number 310 [1/2], 1946
  - The Gulf Aviation Atlas fifth edition (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Handbook of Health, 1943 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Instrument Flight part one Basic Airwork Bureau of Aeronautics U.S. Navy, 04/1943 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Look to the Air Scripps-Howard and Aviation, 1943 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - The Martin Mars Transport [1/2], 1944 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    Oversize item has been separated for storage purposes and is item 00001 in box 0030
  - Ionosphere The Nearness of Distance Man Learns to Multiply his Strength Vol. 3 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Ionosphere The Nearness of Distance Man Learns to Fly Vol. 4 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Keeping Ahead of the Weather, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    by Peter E. Kraght
  - Maps... and how to understand them, 11/1943 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Pilot's Manual Curtiss Electric Propeller (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Trends in Ground and Indirect Expenses in the Certification Domestic Air Transportation Industry, 1947 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Twelve Decades of Railroad Mangement: A History of the Boston & Maine and its Forty-four Constituents, 1830-1952, 05/12/1961 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    by Charles J. Kennedy. The folder contains a draft of chapter 21: The Boston & Maine in the Air
  - United States Supersonic Transport Next Era of Air Travel (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - The Martin Mars Transport [2/2], 1944 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Flight log of TWA Constellation Number 310 [2/2], 1946 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    This item is oversized and was removed from its original folder. There is still material in the original location. That is Box 0026 folder 00005
- Works of art, 1942-1961; MS2092 Series 4; 1 Linear feet
  This series contains color and black and white etchings and posters of airplanes.
  - First Flight two images from Fairchild Packet (Box 28, Folder 7)
    Etching by Kent Hagerman. "First Flight" is the third etching in a series depicted important steps in the development of a modern cargo airplane. This C-119 Packet is the newest Air Force cargo and troop transplant.
  - Etching of airplane and soldier, 1951 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    Etching by Kent Hagerman.
  - Fairchild C-119 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    Etching by Kent Hagerman. Pencil marking "trial run 74/142"
  - Fairchild xc-120 Pack Plane (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Etching of plane (Box 28, Folder 11)
    Etching by Kent Hagerman. Pencil on image "[unintelligable word] assembly Fairchild Packet"
  - The Man Without Fear, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    Text on image "Before dawn on June 2, 1917, a gutty Canadian pilot hedge-hopped his silver Nieuport 17 behind enemy lines to attack a German airdrome single-handedly. He destroyed three Albatros biplanes --bringing his total kills to 47 in less than 3 months of combat flying on the Western Front. This exploit won Billy Bishop the Victoria Cross. The fearless Canadian fought 170 air battles and scored 72 victories. "
    From a print in the Leach Corporation Heritage of the Air Collection.
  - Airdrop to the 'Lost Battalion', 1959 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    Text on image "Banking gently, the D.H.-4 braved a burst of German gunfire and rushed low over the Argonne Forest. The observer began dropping packages. Somewhere below, surrounded by the enemy, lay the injured and dying men of America's "Lost Battalion." It was October 6, 1918--date of the first aerial resupply drop in combat history. The next day an airdrop team spotted the battalion's exact position and the survivors were rescued. "
  - The King of Air Fighters, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    Text on image "Spinning crazily, the S.E. 5a fell from the sky, followed by a German Pfalz. At 5,000 feet, the Hun flattened out to watch the crash. Instead, the S.E. 5a pulled out and headed for home. A flight commander had just saved one of his pilots by drawing the enemy on to himself. Such a man was Britain's Mick Mannock--the greatest fighter pilot of World War I."
  - Great London Air Raid Scare, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    Text on image "After two years of unsuccessful Zeppelin raids, the Germans launched the second phrase of their attempt to panic the English on July 7, 1917. Twenty-two Gotha G. IV heavy bombers dropped 72 bombs in the first of 52 aerial raids. Although tactically unproductive, the bombings had a deep psychological effect that many Britons would remember when, in 1939, they again searched the skies for planes bearing the black cross."
  - Kazakov and his "Katze", 1960 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    Text on image "The Germans couldn't believe their eyes. Behind them, trailing a five-pronged anchor and an iron ball, was a Russian in a Morane scout. He struck from above. The anchor or "Katze" hooked into the left wing of the Albatros and shattered it. Staff-Captain Alexander A. Kazakov scored a victory. It was June, 1915, By 1919, the Russian ace claimed 32 kills and held every decoration his country could award for gallantry."
  - The Arizona Balloon Buster, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    Text on image "As dusk fell over the St. Mihiel front, a lone SPAD piloted by an Arizona cowboy crossed the enemy lines and headed for a German observation balloon. In minutes, the sausage was flaming the earth, and Lt. Frank Luke, Jr. of the 27th Aero Squadron had scored another victory. His record of 15 balloons and 3 planes in 17 days won Luke the Medal of Honor."
  - The Two-Seater Ace, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    Text on image "Out of the mist came nine Germans. Major Andy McKeever swung his Bristol Fighter into position and bagged a flight leader. Thirty seconds later, three enemy planes were falling. McKeever and his observer met a second attack and claimed another kill. Then, their guns shot away, the Britishers ran - and a reconnaissance mission over the battle of Cambrai ended as one of the most heroic exploits of World War I flying."
  - The Red Knight of Germany, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    Text on image "Brilliantly colored German Fokker Dr.-1's ruled the skies in 1917, flying in tight formations introduced by a young Prussian nobleman whose all-scarlet plane identified him as the Red Baron. He was Manfred von Richthofen, destined to become Germany's greatest ace of World War I, with 80 confirmed kills and 126 unofficial victories."
  - Fall of the Flying Fool, 1961 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    Text on image "The Breguet hovered at 2,600 feet, directing artillery fire north of Villers-Cotterets. Suddenly a Fokker D. VIII swept in on its tail. The Breguet's observer sprayed the German with gunfire as the Fokker bucked and fell, the pilot jumped--but his parachute harness hooked on the rudder. Struggling to free himself was Ernst Udet, the German ace. Udet survived to become idolized as "The flying Fool" for his aerobatics in the '20s."
  - Moment of Decision, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    Text on image "The German observer had stopped firing. Puzzled, the American flew his Nieuport 28 in closer to the Rumpler for a good look. He saw the observer standing up, arms folded and empty ammunition belt flapping form the cockpit. Could the American shoot down an unarmed enemy? He hesitated. Then, in a moment of decision, Lt. Douglas Campbell became an American Ace. the Rumpler was his fifth victory."
  - The Killer Camel, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 22)
    Text on image "Fifty feet above the Somme River, time ran out on the life of Baron Manfred von Richthofen, Germany's greatest ace. Behind his red Fokker was Captain Roy Brown in a British-built Sopwith Camel. the Canadian was low on ammunition but began firing as soon as he was within range--and the treacherous Camel, the supreme Allied dogfighter of World War I, claimed another victim."
  - The Strange Story, 1961 (Box 28, Folder 23)
    Text on image "The British pilot clutched his ammunition drum and prayed. Thrown out as his Martinsyde Scout flipped into a spin, he dangled helplessly. The pilot kicked toward the cockpit behind him, finally got his feet hooked inside and jammed on full aileron and elevator. As the Martinsyde righted itself, he fell back into the cockpit and pulled out of the dive. It was an episode Capt Louis A. Strange of the Royal Flying Corps never forgot."
  - Highly supercharged two stage "Twin Wasps" give Grumman Wildcats a big edge over the Japanese as our Navy swings into action to avenge Pearl Harbor, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    This is a black and white illustration by Clayton Knight
  - Poster of war battle titled Sighted Sub Sank Same, 01/1942 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Ensign Donald F. Mason North Atlantic Ocean, January, 1942 Lockheed "Hudson" patron bomber (U.S. Navy)"
  - Poster of planes in battle titled Butch O'Hara, 02/1942 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Lieut. Comdr. Edward H. O'Hare Gilbert Islands, February, 1942 Grumman "Wildcat" Fighter Mitsubishi 96 Bombers (U.S. Navy)"
  - Poster of planes in battle titled Bombers over Benghazi, 07/1942 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Maj. Gen. Lewis H. Brereton, Commanding Benghazi, Eqypt, July, 1942 Consolidated B-24 Bombers Macchi C-200 Fighters (U.S. Navy)"
  - Poster of plane and men in raft titled Carribean Rescue, 04/1942 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Ensign Francis Pinter Carribean Sea, April, 1942 Consolidated PBY Flying Boat (U.S. Navy)"
  - Poster of planes in battle titled Battle of Midway, 06/1942 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Ensign G. H. Gay Midway Island, June, 1942 Douglas TBD Torpedo Plane Japanese Zero Fighters (U.S. Navy)"
  - Poster of planes in battle titled Marines Over the Solomons, 08/1942 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Maj. Richard Mangrum, Commanding Solomon Island, August 1942 Douglas SBD Dive Bombers (U.S. Marines)"
  - Poster of planes in battle titled First U.S. Raid over Europe, 07/04/1942 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Capt. Charles C. Kegelman Valkenburg, Netherlands, July 4, 1942 Douglas A-20A Light Bombers Focke-Wulf FW 190 Pursuits (U.S. army Air Forces)"
  - Poster of planes in battle titled Caught in Kiska, 10/1942 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    Color poster by Charles H. Hubbell. Text on image "Capt. M.A. Beth, Commanding Aleutian Islands, October 1942 Martin B-26 "Marauder" Medium Bombers (U.S. army Air Forces)"
  - Mission Accomplished (Box 29, Folder 12)
    by Charles M. Capps. Text with image "Symbolic of victory in its homeward flight... a Boeing B-29 Superfortress casts its shadow over the snow of a typically American rural winter scene in this reproduction, actual size, of an etching by Charles M. Capps, well-known Kansas artist. The original is a combination of the soft-ground and aquatint processes, a limited edition owned by Boeing-Wichita."
  - Fighting Aircraft of America (Box 29, Folder 13)
    A folio from the Propeller Division, Curtiss-Wright Corporation. Color images of planes include: Stratosphere Patrol, Skyrocket, Fying Torpedo, Liberator, Lightning, Mustang, Troopship, Buffalo, Mariner, Lancer, Tomahawk, Aircobra, and Helldiver.
  - The Sinking of the Kensington Court (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Image of a sinking ship and the planes that appear to have sunk it.